<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true discourse of the late battaile fought betweene our Englishmen, and the Prince of Parma, on Monday the 15. of Nouember 1585 and of such towers and cities as are of late conquered and brought to the Queenes Maiesties subiection, by that valiant gentleman M. Norris.</title>
            <author>W. M., servitour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1585</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845420</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845420</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10317</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06706)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10317)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 431:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true discourse of the late battaile fought betweene our Englishmen, and the Prince of Parma, on Monday the 15. of Nouember 1585 and of such towers and cities as are of late conquered and brought to the Queenes Maiesties subiection, by that valiant gentleman M. Norris.</title>
                  <author>W. M., servitour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Roger Ward, dwelling néere vnto Holburne Conduit,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1585.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W.M. seruitour.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Norris, John, --  Sir, 1547?-1597.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10317:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10317:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A True Diſcourſe of the late Battaile fought betweene our</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, and the Prince of <hi>Parma,</hi> on Monday the 15. of Nouember 1585. and of ſuch Towers and Cities as are of late conquered and brought to the Queenes Maieſties ſubiection, by that valiant gentleman M. <hi>Norris.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>R W</head>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Roger Ward, consisting of a pheasant upon a wreath within an ornamental frame, with the printer's initials at the side</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Roger Ward,</hi> dwelling néere vnto <hi>Holburne Conduit,</hi> 1585.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10317:2"/>
            <head>To his very friend W. G. gentleman in London.</head>
            <p>FOr aſmuch as the nature of man is alwaies deſirous of nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that diuers people are giuen to ſpeake d uerſly, ſome for fauour, and ſome for malice, making ſundrye reportes of one matter either adding or diminiſhing, as beſt it fitteth their fancies, or according as they beare in affection. Therefore that my frendes in England may be fully certified of the truth of our lateſt affaires, I haue ſent you here a certaine draught of our attemptes, ſince our ariuall into theſe partes of Flaunders: the truth whereof you neede not to doubt, for that my pen hath written nothing but what my owne eies haue behelde and ſeene. Therfore as you eſteeme of my deedes giue credit to my wordes, and as you haue, tryed my truth, make accoumpt of my tydings, the contents whereof doth briefly follow.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend W. M. ſeruitour vnder Corronall Norris.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10317:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>FTER</hi> it had pleaſed the Quéenes moſt excellent Maieſtie, with the conſent of her graue and honorable counſaile to ſend ſuccour to the poore afflicted and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people of the lowe Countries, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might be defended from the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and crueltie of their bloudie eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which hath ſo many yeares endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the miſerie of deadly warres, and onely for their auncient li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and the cauſe of their conſciences, which hath againſt right bene holden from them by the meanes of the King of Spaine: whereby the countrie hath bene conſumed, the inhabitaunc<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpoyled, and all things brought almoſt into deſſolution: in ſo much the poore people remained ſuckerleſſe, till it pleaſed her graciou<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Maieſtie to yeelde them reliefe. Since which time her Noble Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie haue not ſpent their time in vaine, but to the honour of their countrie, and the ioy of all her Maieſties faithfull ſubiectes, haue ſo valiantly behaued themſelues, that by the helpe of the moſte mightie God (who hath wonderfully proſpered their procéedings) they haue giuen their enimies the repulce from diuers places, and gained ſundrie Tounes and Cities vnto the Quéenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties vſe. If then the magnanimitie of noble mindes may bee iudged by outward workes, and zealous hartes towardes God and Prince, may be meaſured and made apparant by manfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploites and cruell conflictes tending to no leſſe then the loſſe of liues, and confuſion of common weales, what may wee ſaye of theſe late victorious conqueſtes, gained by Gods prouidence, and their aduentures, who haue put themſelues in the hazard of ſo many enimies-hands, whoſe inſatiable panche<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> haue bene glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the bloud of ſo many good and faithful profeſſours, whoſe bullets rebounding from the breaſts of our valiant defenders, hath recoyled into their owne boſomes, as in <hi>Flaunders</hi> hath of late bene ſeene acchiued, by thoſe worthy men the only inſtruments appointed by Gods grace and her Maieſties prouidence, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the tyrannie of thoſe proude, inſolent and preſumptuous Spaniardes, whoſe f<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rce the moſt part of theſe people haue felt, to their great griefe, and our immortall glorie: by <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full proweſſe, and dexteritie in marciall affaires, the frontiue
<pb facs="tcp:10317:3"/> townes of Holland and Zealand be alreadie giuen vp to her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſtie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> in them <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> at <hi>Bull,</hi> and in <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ng,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſides <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Burga<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> the very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into <hi>Fl<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ders</hi> and <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ba<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t:</hi> Likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>Williamſtut,</hi> and the land of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>agon.</hi> All which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> her Maieſties gouernment beſides that valiant and hard cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine M. <hi>Norris</hi> is now in <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>derland,</hi> whereby <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>e he hath made ſuch an <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> that many multit<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes can hardly repute it againe, ſo many bulwarkes hath hee beaten downe: and ſo many mightie walles hath hee caſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foote. Alſo by force of Armes and the helpe of God he hath taken the Sconce of <hi>Arn<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which was erected hard by a riuer ſide: wherein <hi>M. Norris</hi> for the better ſucceſſe in the enterpriſe, placed fiue ſhips, and two dayes, which ſped very <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for that they were <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                  <desc>…</desc>
               </gap>d, and in the enimies reach, knowing no way to eſcape the <gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ent daunger: Which captaine <hi>Hunnings</hi> perceiuing, and ſeeking to eſcape the enimies handes, being already ſore hurt, thought to leape out of a ſhip into a boate: but by reaſon of his Armour which he had on that time, he lighted ſhort, and by that meanes, was vnfortunately drowned Notwithſtanding <hi>M. Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> ſtill continued his ſkermiſh on land (in a ſconce which he had butted againſt them) ſo manfully, that hauing ſore diſcomfited them by meanes of his force and hote aſſalte: and the day draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neere to an ende they reſted.</p>
            <figure>
               <pb facs="tcp:10317:3"/>
               <head>A</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Thus haue you heard the true reporte of theſe laſt exploytes in Flaunders, which God increaſe for the glorie of his name, and proſper all their Counſailes, and affaires, in this their godly and rightfull cauſe to the comfort of the poore afflcted people of that troubleſome countrey, and the honour of her royall Maieſtie by whoſe mercifull and bountefull hand the opreſſed are defended &amp; relieued. For whoſe happie and continuall raigne all faithfull ſubiectes may hartely pray that many yeares ſhe may raigne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs.</p>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <list>
                  <head>Here followeth the names of ſuch Captaines as were hurt at the winning of Arnam ſcence.</head>
                  <item>Captaine Bowrowes.</item>
                  <item>Captaine Wotton,</item>
                  <item>Captaine Knowles.</item>
                  <item>Captaine Blunt.</item>
                  <item>Captaine Vaurſor.</item>
                  <item>Captaine Wilſon.</item>
               </list>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:10317:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
